ⓘ These English & Foreign subtitles created by ZoowlCZ (ver. 2025-08) are an expanded version of the English subtitles (6053820) uploaded by lusiads to OpenSubtitles.
[Sindarin] ♫ Estel, le iôn adar lín... ♫
[English] ♫ Hope, you are your father’s son... ♫
[Sindarin] ♫ ... û iôn naneth lín. ♫
[English] ♫ ... not your mother’s child. ♫
[Sindarin] Anirne hene beriad i chên lîn.
[English] She wanted to protect her child.
[Sindarin] Ned Imladris nauthant e le beriathar aen.
[English] She thought in Rivendell you would be safe.
In her heart, your mother knew
you'd be hunted all your life.
That you'd never escape your fate.
The skill of the elves can reforge
the sword of kings...
...but only you have the power to wield it.
I do not want that power.
I have never wanted it.
You are the last of that bloodline.
There is no other.
My old sword! Sting.
Here, take it. Take it.
- It's so light.
- Yes, yeah. Made by the elves, you know.
The blade glows blue when orcs are close.
And it's times like that, my lad,
when you have to be extra careful.
Here's a pretty thing.
Mithril.
As light as a feather, and as hard as dragon scales.
Let me see you put it on. Come on.
My old ring.
I should very much like...
...to hold it again, one last time.
I'm sorry I brought this upon you, my boy.
I'm sorry that you must carry this burden.
I'm sorry for everything.
The ring-bearer is setting out
on the quest of Mount Doom.
On you who travel with him, no oath...
...nor bond is laid to go further than you will.
Farewell. Hold to your purpose.
May the blessings of elves and men...
...and all free folk go with you.
The fellowship awaits the ring-bearer.
Mordor, Gandalf, is it left or right?
Left.
We must hold to this course, west
of the Misty Mountains, for 40 days.
If our luck holds, the Gap of Rohan
will still be open to us.
From there, our road turns east to Mordor.
Two, one, five. Good! Very good.
Move your feet.
- You look good, Pippin.
- Thanks.
Faster!
If anyone was to ask for my opinion,
which I note they're not...
...I'd say we were taking the long way 'round.
Gandalf.
We could pass through the mines of Moria.
My cousin Balin would give us a royal welcome.
No Gimli, I would not take the road through
Moria unless I had no other choice.
Sorry!
Get him!
- For the Shire!
- Hold him. Hold him down, Merry!
Gentlemen, that's enough.
You've got my arm!
- What is that?
- Nothing. It's just a wisp of cloud.
It's moving fast.
Against the wind.
- Crebain from Dunland!
- Hide!
- Hurry!
- Take cover!
Spies of Saruman.
The passage south is being watched.
We must take the pass of Caradhras.
Frodo!
[Quenya] ♫ I tuo, i macil... ♫
[English] ♫ The strength, The weapon... ♫
Boromir.
It is a strange fate that we should
suffer so much fear and doubt...
[Quenya] ♫ Astaldoron mauri... ♫
[English] ♫ The needs of the valiant... ♫
...over so small a thing.
[Quenya] ♫ Nai túren... ♫
[English] ♫ Be it that victory... ♫
Such a little thing.
Boromir!
Give the ring to Frodo.
As you wish.
I care not.
So, Gandalf, you try to lead them over Caradhras.
And if that fails, where then will you go?
If the mountain defeats you...
... will you risk a more dangerous road?
[Quenya] Cuiva nwalca Carnirassë!
[English] Wake up cruel Redhorn!
There is a fell voice on the air.
It's Saruman!
He's trying to bring down the mountain!
Gandalf, we must turn back!
No!
[Sindarin] Losto Caradhras, Sedho! Hodo!
[English] Sleep Redhorn, Be still! Lie Still!
[Sindarin] Nuitho i 'Ruith!
[English] Hold your Wrath!
[Quenya] Cuiva nwalca Carnirassë!
[English] Wake up cruel Redhorn!
[Quenya] Nai yarvaxëa rasselya...
[English] May your bloodstained horn...
[Quenya] ...taltuva ñotto-carinnar!
[English] ...fall upon enemy heads!
We must get off the mountain!
Make for the Gap of Rohan,
and take the west road to my city!
The Gap of Rohan takes us too close to Isengard!
We cannot pass over a mountain.
Let us go under it.
Let us go through the mines of Moria.
Moria. You fear to go into those mines.
The dwarves delved too greedily and too deep.
You know what they awoke
in the darkness of Khazad-dûm:
Shadow and flame.
Let the ring-bearer decide.
We cannot stay here!
This will be the death of the hobbits.
Frodo?
We will go through the mines.
So be it.
Frodo, come and help an old man.
How is your shoulder?
- Better than it was.
- And the ring?
You feel its power growing, don't you?
I've felt it too.
You must be careful now.
Evil will be drawn to you from
outside the fellowship.
And, I fear, from within.
- Who then do I trust?
- You must trust yourself.
Trust your own strengths.
- What do you mean?
- There are many powers in this world...
...for good or for evil.
Some are greater than I am.
And against some I have not yet been tested.
The walls...
...of Moria.
Dwarf doors are invisible when closed.
Yes, Gimli, their own masters cannot find
them if their secrets are forgotten.
Why doesn't that surprise me?
Well, let's see.
Ithildin.
It mirrors only starlight and moonlight.
It reads; "The Doors of Durin, Lord of Moria.
- Speak, friend, and enter."
- What do you suppose that means?
Oh It's quite simple. If you are a friend,
you speak the password and the doors will open.
[Sindarin] Annon Edhellen edro hi ammen!
[English] Gate of the elves, open now for me!
[Sindarin] Fennas Nogothrim, lasto beth lammen.
[English] Doorway of the Dwarf-folk, listen to the word of my tongue.
Nothing's happening.
I once knew every spell in
all the tongues of elves...
...men and orcs.
What are you going to do, then?
Knock your head against these doors,
Peregrin Took!
And if that does not shatter them...
...and I am allowed a little
peace from foolish questions...
...I will try to find the opening words.
[Quenya] Ando Eldarinwa...
[English] Gate of elves...
[Quenya] ...a lasta quettanya...
[English] ...listen to my word...
[Quenya] ...fenda casarinwa!
[English] ...threshold of dwarves!
Mines are no place for a pony.
- Even one so brave as Bill.
- Bye-bye, Bill.
Fennas Nogothrim...
(Doorway of the dwarf-folk...)
Go on, Bill. Go on.
Don't worry, Sam, he knows the way home.
Do not disturb the water.
Oh, it's useless.
It's a riddle.
"Speak 'friend' and enter."
What's the elvish word for "friend"?
[Sindarin] Mellon.
[English] Friend.
Mellon.
Soon, master elf, you will enjoy
the fabled hospitality of the dwarves.
Roaring fires, malt beer, ripe meat off the bone!
This, my friend, is the home of my cousin Balin.
And they call it a mine.
A mine!
This is no mine. It's a tomb.
No....
No!
Goblins.
We make for the Gap of Rohan.
We should never have come here.
Now, get out of here. Get out!
- Frodo!
- Help!
Strider!
- Get off him!
Aragorn!
Frodo!
Into the mines!
- Legolas!
- Into the cave!
Run!
We now have but one choice.
We must face the long dark of Moria.
Be on your guard.
There are older and fouler things than orcs...
...in the deep places of the world.
Quietly now.
It's a four-day journey to the other side.
Let us hope that our presence may go unnoticed.
The wealth of Moria was not in gold...
...or jewels...
...but mithril.
Bilbo had a shirt of mithril rings
that Thorin gave him.
- Oh, that was a kingly gift.
- Yes.
I never told him...
...but its worth was greater
than the value of the Shire.
Pippin.
I have no memory of this place.
- Are we Lost?
- No.
- I think we are.
- Gandalf's thinking.
- Merry?
- What?
I'm hungry.
- There's something down there.
- It's Gollum.
- Gollum?
- He's been following us for three days.
- He escaped the dungeons of Barad-dûr?
- Escaped...
...or was set loose.
Now the ring has brought him here.
He will never be rid of his need for it.
He hates and loves the ring,
as he hates and loves himseIf.
Smeagol's life is a sad story.
Yes, Smeagol he was once called.
Before the ring found him.
Before it drove him mad.
It's a pity Bilbo didn't kill him
when he had the chance.
Pity?
It is pity that stayed Bilbo's hand.
Many that live deserve death.
Some that die deserve life.
Can you give it to them, Frodo?
Do not be too eager to deal
out death and judgment.
Even the very wise cannot see all ends.
My heart tells me that Gollum has some
part to play yet, for good or ill...
...before this is over.
The pity of Bilbo may rule the fate of many.
I wish the ring had never come to me.
I wish none of this had happened.
So do all who live to see such times.
But that is not for them to decide.
All we have to decide is what to do
with the time that is given to us.
There are other forces at work in this
world, Frodo, besides the will of evil.
Bilbo was meant to find the ring.
In which case, you also were meant to have it.
And that is an encouraging thought.
It's that way.
- He's remembered.
- No.
But the air doesn't smell so foul down here.
If in doubt, Meriadoc, always follow your nose.
Let me risk a little more light.
Behold...
...the great realm and dwarf-city of Dwarrowdelf.
Now there's an eye opener, and no mistake.
Gimli!
No!
Oh, no.
No.
"Here lies Balin...
...son of Fundin...
...Lord of Moria."
He is dead, then.
It's as I feared.
We must move on. We cannot linger.
"They have taken the bridge and the second hall.
We have barred the gates...
...but cannot hold them for long.
The ground shakes.
Drums...
...drums in the deep.
We cannot get out.
A shadow moves in the dark.
They are coming."
Fool of a Took!
Throw yourself in next time,
and rid us of your stupidity.
Frodo!
Orcs.
Get back! Stay close to Gandalf!
They have a cave-troll.
Let them come!
There is one dwarf yet in Moria
who still draws breath.
I think I'm getting the hang of this.
Frodo!
Aragorn! Aragorn!
Oh, no.
He's alive.
I'm all right. I'm not hurt.
You should be dead.
That spear would have skewered a wild boar.
I think there's more to this
hobbit than meets the eye.
Mithril.
You are full of surprises, Master Baggins.
To the bridge of Khazad-dûm!
This way!
What is this new devilry?
A Balrog.
A demon of the ancient world.
This foe is beyond any of you.
Run!
Quickly!
Gandalf.
Lead them on, Aragorn.
The bridge is near.
Do as I say!
Swords are no more use here.
Gandalf!
Merry! Pippin!
Sam!
Nobody tosses a Dwarf.
Not the beard!
Steady.
Hold on!
Hang on!
Lean forward!
Steady.
Come on!
Now!
Over the bridge!
Fly!
You cannot pass!
Gandalf!
I am a servant of the secret fire,
wielder of the flame of Anor.
The dark fire will not avail you, flame of Udûn!
Go back to the Shadow.
YOU - SHALL NOT - PASS!
- No! No!
- Gandalf!
Fly, you fools!
No!
Aragorn!
Legolas, get them up.
Give them a moment, for pity's sake!
By nightfall, these hills will be swarming with orcs.
We must reach the woods of Lothlórien.
Come, Boromir. Legolas.
Gimli, get them up.
On your feet, Sam.
Frodo?
Frodo!
[Sindarin] ♫ Man ammen toltha i dann hen morn? ♫
[English] ♫ Who brings to us this token of darkness? ♫
[Sindarin] ♫ Si dannatha, nauva. ♫
[English] ♫ Will now fall, will be. ♫
Stay close, young hobbits!
They say that a great sorceress
lives in these woods.
[Quenya] ♫ Mel~ Melma nóren sina... ♫
[English] ♫ Love for this land... ♫
An elf-witch...
...of terrible power.
All who look upon her...
[Quenya] ♫ ...núra ala eäro núr. ♫
[English] ♫ ...greater than sea deeps. ♫
...fall under her spell.
Frodo!
And are never seen again.
Your coming to us is as the footsteps of doom.
You bring great evil here, ring-bearer.
Mr. Frodo?
Well, here's one dwarf she won't ensnare so easily.
I have the eyes of a hawk and the ears of a fox.
The dwarf breathes so loud, we
could have shot him in the dark.
[Sindarin] Mae govannen, Legolas Thranduilion.
[English] Welcome, Legolas son of Thranduil.
[Sindarin] Govannas vîn gwennen le, Haldir o Lórien.
[English] Our fellowship stands in your debt, Haldir of Lórien.
[Sindarin] A Aragorn in Dúnedain...
[English] Oh, Aragorn of the Dúnedain...
[Sindarin] ...istannen le ammen.
[English] ...you are known to us.
Haldir.
So much for the legendary courtesy of the elves!
Speak words we can all understand!
We have not had dealings with
the dwarves since the dark days.
And you know what this dwarf says to that?
Ishkhaqwi ai durugnul!
(I spit upon your grave!)
That was not so courteous.
You bring great evil with you.
You can go no further.
[Sindarin] Boe ammen veriad lîn. Andelu i ven!
[English] We need your protection. The road is too dangerous!
[Sindarin] Merin le telim.
[English] I wish we may come with you.
[Sindarin] Boe ammen i dulu lîn!
[English] We need your support!
Aragorn!
[Sindarin] Merin le telim.
[English] I wish we may come with you.
[Sindarin] Andelu i ven!
[English] The road is too dangerous!
Gandalf's death was not in vain.
Nor would he have you give up hope.
You carry a heavy burden, Frodo.
Don't carry the weight of the dead.
You will follow me.
Caras Galadhon.
The heart of Elvendom on earth.
Realm of the Lord Celeborn
and of Galadriel, Lady of Light.
[Quenya] ♫ Ela i cá ♫
[English] ♫ Behold the light! ♫
[Quenya] ♫ Nenya sina... ♫
[English] ♫ Nenya is this... ♫
[Quenya] ♫ ...corma úhátima... ♫
[English] ♫ ...ring unbreakable... ♫
[Quenya] ♫ ...i haryanye. ♫
[English] ♫ ...that I possess. ♫
The enemy knows you have entered here.
What hope you had in secrecy is now gone.
Eight there are here, yet nine there
were set out from Rivendell.
Tell me, where is Gandalf?
For I much desire to speak with him.
I can no longer see him from afar.
Gandalf the Grey did not pass
the borders of this land.
He has fallen into shadow.
He was taken by both shadow and flame.
A Balrog of Morgoth.
For we went needlessly into the net of Moria.
Needless were none of the deeds of Gandalf in life.
We do not yet know his full purpose.
Do not let the great emptiness
of Khazad-dûm fill your heart...
...Gimli, son of Gloin.
For the world has grown full of peril...
...and in all lands...
...love is now mingled with grief.
What now becomes of this fellowship?
Without Gandalf, hope is lost.
The quest stands upon the edge of a knife.
Stray but a little and it will fail...
...to the ruin of all.
Yet hope remains while the company is true.
Do not let your hearts be troubled.
Go now and rest...
...for you are weary with sorrow and much toil.
Tonight, you will sleep....
Welcome, Frodo of the Shire...
...one who has seen the eye!
[Sindarin chorus] ♫  In gwidh ristennin...  ♫
[English] ♫ The bonds cut... ♫
[Quenya solo] ♫  Ilfirin nairelma.  ♫
[English] ♫ Undying is our regret. ♫
[Sindarin chorus] ♫  ...i fae narchannen.  ♫
[English] ♫ ...the spirit broken. ♫
A lament for Gandalf.
[Quenya solo] ♫  Nauva i nauva.  ♫
[English] ♫ What should be shall be. ♫
[Sindarin chorus] ♫  I Lach Anor ed...   ♫
[English] ♫ The Flame of Anor out... ♫
What do they say about him?
I have not the heart to tell you.
For me, the grief is still too near.
[Quenya solo] ♫  Ilfirin nairelma...  ♫
[English] ♫ Undying is our regret... ♫
I bet they don't mention his fireworks.
There should be a verse about them.
[Sindarin chorus] ♫  ...ardhon gwannen.   ♫
[English] ♫ ...left this world. ♫
[Quenya solo] ♫  ...ar ullume nucuvalme.  ♫
[English] ♫ ...yet we will cast all away. ♫
The finest rockets ever seen
[Sindarin chorus] ♫  Mithrandir, a Randir Vithren...  ♫
[English] ♫ Mithrandir, o Pilgrim Grey... ♫
They burst in stars of blue and green
Or after thunder, silver showers
Came falling like a rain of flowers
[Sindarin chorus] ♫  ...ú-reniathach...  ♫
[English] ♫ ...you will not journey... ♫
Oh, that doesn't do them justice by a long road.
[Quenya solo] ♫  Nauva i nauva.  ♫
[English] ♫ What should be shall be. ♫
[Sindarin chorus] ♫  ...i amar galen.  ♫
[English] ♫ ...the world green. ♫
Take some rest.
[Quenya solo] ♫  Melme nóren sina...  ♫
[English] ♫ Love for this land... ♫
These borders are well-protected.
I will find no rest here.
[Sindarin chorus] ♫  I reniad lín ne môr nuithannen.  ♫
[English] ♫ The journey of you in darkness stopped. ♫
I heard her voice inside my head.
She spoke of my father and the fall of Gondor.
She said to me; "Even now there is hope Left."
[Quenya solo] ♫  Ilfirin nairelma...  ♫
[English] ♫ Undying is our regret... ♫
But I cannot see it.
It is long since we had any hope.
[Quenya solo] ♫  ...ar ullume nucuvalme.  ♫
[English] ♫ ...yet we will cast all away. ♫
My father is a noble man.
But his rule is failing...
...and our people lose faith.
He looks to me to make things right,
and I would do it.
I would see the glory of Gondor restored.
Have you ever seen it, Aragorn?
The white tower of Ecthelion.
Glimmering like a spike of pearl and silver.
Its banners caught high in the morning breeze.
Have you ever been called home...
...by the clear ringing of silver trumpets?
I have seen the white city...
...long ago.
One day, our paths will lead us there.
And the tower guard shall take up the call:
"The Lords of Gondor have returned."
Will you look into the mirror?
What will I see?
Even the wisest cannot tell.
For the mirror...
...shows many things.
Things that were...
...things that are...
...and some things...
...that have not yet come to pass.
I know what it is you saw.
For it is also in my mind.
It is what will come to pass if you should fail.
The fellowship is breaking.
It is already begun.
He will try to take the ring.
You know of whom I speak.
One by one, it will destroy them all.
If you ask it of me...
... I will give you the one ring.
You offer it to me freely.
I do not deny that my heart
has greatly desired this.
In place of a dark lord, you would have a queen...
...not dark but beautiful and terrible as the dawn!
Treacherous as the sea!
Stronger than the foundations of the earth!
All shall love me...
...and despair.
I pass the test. I will diminish...
...and go into the West...
...and remain Galadriel.
- I cannot do this alone.
You are a ring-bearer, Frodo.
To bear a ring of power...
...is to be alone.
This is Nenya, the ring of Adamant.
And I am its keeper.
This task was appointed to you.
And if you do not find a way...
...no one will.
Then I know what I must do.
It's just...
...I'm afraid to do it.
Even the smallest person can change
the course of the future.
Do you know how the orcs first came into being?
They were elves once.
Taken by the dark powers...
...tortured and mutilated.
A ruined and terrible form of life.
And now...
...perfected.
My fighting Uruk-hai...
...whom do you serve?
Saruman!
Hunt them down. Do not stop until, they are found.
You do not know pain.
You do not know fear.
You will taste man-flesh!
One of the halflings carries
something of great value.
Bring them to me alive and unspoiled.
Kill the others.
[Quenya] ♫  Ai! Laurië lantar lassi súrinen.  ♫
[English] ♫ Alas! Like gold fall leaves in the wind. ♫
Never before have we clad strangers
in the garb of our own people.
May these cloaks help shield
you from unfriendly eyes.
Lembas.
Elvish waybread.
One small bite is enough to fill
the stomach of a grown man.
How many did you eat?
Four.
Every league you travel south,
the danger will increase.
Mordor orcs now hold the
eastern shore of the Anduin.
Nor will you find safety on the western bank.
Strange creatures bearing the mark of the
white hand have been seen on our borders.
Seldom do orcs journey in the open
under the sun, yet these have done so.
[Sindarin] Le aphadar aen.
[English] You are being tracked.
By river you have the chance of outrunning
the enemy to the falls of Rauros.
My gift for you, Legolas, is a bow of the Galadhrim.
Worthy of the skill of our woodland kin.
These are the daggers of the Noldorin.
They have already seen service in war.
Do not fear, young Peregrin Took.
You will find your courage.
And for you, Samwise Gamgee...
...Elven rope made of hithlain.
Thank you, my lady.
Have you run out of those nice, shiny daggers?
And what gift would a dwarf ask of the elves?
Nothing.
Except to look upon the lady
of the Galadhrim one last time...
...for she is more fair than all
the jewels beneath the earth.
Actually....
There was one thing.
No, no, I couldn't.
It's quite impossible.
Stupid to ask.
I have nothing greater to give...
...than the gift you already bear.
[Sindarin] Am meleth dîn...
[English] For her love...
[Sindarin] ...I ant e guil Arwen Undómiel pígatha.
[English] ...the gift of life of Arwen will fade.
[Sindarin] Aníron i e broniatha...
[English] I wish that she endures...
[Sindarin] ...Ad ae periatham athar i methid en-amar hen.
[English] ...even if we separate beyond the limits of this world.
[Sindarin] Aníron i e círatha na Valinor.
[English] I wish that she sails to Valinor.
That choice is yet before her.
You have your own choice to make, Aragorn.
To rise above the height of all your
fathers since the days of Elendil...
...or to fall into darkness
with all that is left of your kin.
[Quenya] Namárië.
[English] Farewell.
[Sindarin] Nadath nâ i moe cerich...
[English] There is much you have yet to do...
[Sindarin] ...dan...
[English] ...but...
[Sindarin] ...ú-'eveditham, Elessar.
[English] ...we shall not meet again, Elessar.
Farewell, Frodo Baggins.
I give you the light of Earendil...
...our most beloved star.
May it be a light for you in dark places...
... when all other lights go out.
I have taken my worst wound at this parting...
...having looked my last upon that which is fairest.
Henceforth I will call nothing fair
unless it be her gift to me.
What was her gift?
I asked her for one hair from her golden head.
She gave me three.
Gollum. He has tracked us since Moria.
I had hoped we would lose him on the river.
But he's too clever a waterman.
And if he alerts the enemy to our whereabouts...
...it will make the crossing even more dangerous.
Have some food, Mr. Frodo.
- No, Sam.
- You haven't eaten anything all day.
You're not sleeping, neither.
Don't think I haven't noticed.
- Mr. Frodo
- I'm all right.
But you're not.
I'm here to help you.
I promised Gandalf that I would.
You can't help me, Sam.
Not this time.
Get some sleep.
Minas Tirith is the safer road.
You know that.
From there we can regroup.
Strike out for Mordor from a place of strength.
There is no strength in Gondor that can avail us.
You were quick enough to trust the elves.
Have you so little faith in your own people?
Yes, there is weakness.
There is frailty.
But there is courage also,
and honor to be found in men.
But you will not see that.
You are afraid!
All your life, you have hidden in the shadows.
Scared of who you are, of what you are.
I will not lead the ring within
a hundred leagues of your city.
Frodo.
The Argonath.
[Quenya] ♫  Et Eärello, Endorenna utúlien.  ♫
[English] ♫ Out of the Great Sea, to Middle-earth I am come. ♫
Long have I desired to look upon the kings of old.
My kin.
[Quenya] ♫  Sinome, maruvan, ar hildinyar.  ♫
[English] ♫ In this place, I will abide, and my heirs. ♫
We cross the lake at nightfall.
Hide the boats and continue on foot.
- We approach Mordor from the North.
- Oh, yes?
Just a simple matter of finding
our way through Emyn Muil...
...an impassable labyrinth of razor-sharp rocks.
And after that, it gets even better.
Festering, stinking marshland
as far as the eye can see.
That is our road.
I suggest you take some rest and
recover your strength, Master Dwarf.
Recover my...
- We should Leave now.
- No.
Orcs patrol the eastern shore.
We must wait for cover of darkness.
It is not the eastern shore that worries me.
A shadow and a threat has
been growing in my mind.
Something draws near.
I can feel it.
Recover strength?
Pay no heed to that, young hobbit.
Where's Frodo?
None of us should wander alone.
You, least of all.
So much depends on you.
Frodo?
I know why you seek solitude.
You suffer. I see it day by day.
You sure you do not suffer needlessly?
There are other ways, Frodo.
- Other paths that we might take.
- I know what you would say.
It would seem like wisdom but
for the warning in my heart.
Warning...against what?
We're all afraid, Frodo.
But to let that fear drive us,
to destroy what hope we have...
...don't you see that is madness?
- There is no other way.
I ask only for the strength to defend my people!
- If you would but lend me the ring.
- No.
- Why do you recoil? I am no thief.
- You are not yourself.
What chance do you think you have?
They will find you.
They will take the ring.
And you will beg for death before the end!
You fool!
It is not yours, save by unhappy chance!
It could have been mine.
It should be mine! Give it to me!
- Give it to me!
- No!
- No.
I see your mind.
You will take the ring to Sauron!
You will betray us!
You'll go to your death, and the death of us all!
Curse you!
Curse you and all the halflings!
Frodo?
Frodo.
What have I done?
Please, Frodo.
Frodo, I'm sorry!
[Black Speech] Akha...
[English] Here...
[Black Speech] ...ashi...
[English] ...only...
Ash Ghurûm
(They will fall)
[Black Speech] ...gurum!
[English] ...death!
Frodo?
- It has taken Boromir.
- Where is the ring?
Stay away!
Frodo!
- I swore to protect you.
- Can you protect me from yourself?
[Quenya] ♫  I tuo, i macil.  ♫
[English] ♫ The strength, The weapon. ♫
Would you destroy it?
Aragorn.
Elessar.
I would have gone with you to the end.
Into the very fires of Mordor.
I know.
Look after the others. Especially Sam.
He will not understand.
Go, Frodo!
Run.
Run!
Mr. Frodo!
Find the halfling!
Elendil!
Aragorn, go!
Frodo!
Hide here. Quick!
Come on!
What's he doing?
He's leaving.
- No!
- Pippin!
Run, Frodo. Go!
- Hey! Hey, you!
- Over here!
- This way!
- It's working!
- I know it's working! Run!
- The horn of Gondor.
- Boromir.
Run!
No.
- They took the little ones.
- Hold still.
Frodo. Where is Frodo?
I let Frodo go.
Then you did what I could not.
I tried to take the ring from him.
- The ring is beyond our reach now.
- Forgive me.
I did not see it.
- I have failed you all.
- No, Boromir.
You fought bravely.
You have kept your honor.
Leave it.
It is over.
The world of men will fall and
all will come to darkness...
...and my city to ruin.
I do not know what strength is in my blood...
...but I swear to you, I will
not let the white city fall...
...nor our people fail.
Our people.
I would have followed you, my brother.
My captain.
My king.
Be at peace...
...son of Gondor.
They will look for his coming from the white tower.
But he will not return.
Frodo!
I wish the ring had never come to me.
I wish none of this had happened.
So do all who live to see such times...
...but that is not for them to decide.
All you have to decide...
...is what to do with the time that is given to you.
Frodo, no!
Frodo!
- Mr. Frodo!
- No, Sam.
Go back, Sam!
- I'm going to Mordor alone.
- Of course you are.
And I'm coming with you!
You can't swim!
Sam!
I made a promise, Mr. Frodo.
A promise:
"Don't you leave him, Samwise Gamgee."
And I don't mean to.
I don't mean to.
Oh Sam.
Come on.
Hurry! Frodo and Sam have
reached the eastern shore.
- You mean not to follow them.
- Frodo's fate is no longer in our hands.
Then it has all been in vain.
The fellowship has failed.
Not if we hold true to each other.
We will not abandon Merry and
Pippin to torment and death.
Not while we have strength left.
Leave all that can be spared behind.
We travel light.
Let us hunt some orc.
Yes!
Mordor.
I hope the others find a safer road.
Strider will look after them.
I don't suppose we'll ever see them again.
We may yet, Mr. Frodo.
We may.
Sam...
...I'm glad you are with me.